Lewis W. Douglas papers, 1859-1974 (bulk 1880-1960)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Lewis W. Douglas papers, 1859-1974 (bulk 1880-1960)
AZ 290
Douglas, Lewis W. (Lewis Williams), 1894-
Correspondence, congressional bills, speeches, articles, financial records, clippings, diaries, reminiscenses, photographs of family members from 1897 to 1964, wills, and estate records relating to Lewis's family and his extensive activities in politics and government.
237 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Lewis W. Douglas was a businessman, Democratic politician, philanthropist, and diplomat. He served in the Arizona State Legislature, 1922-1925; U.S. House of Representatives, 1927-1933; U.S. Budget Director, 1933-1934; President of McGill University, 1938-1939; head of U.S. War Shipping Administration, 1942-1944; and Ambassador to Great Britain, 1947- 1950. His father, James Stuart Douglas (1868-1949), was a mine owner and banker; his grandfather, James Douglas (1837-1918), was a mining engineer, metallurgist, and industrialist.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: James Douglas Papers, 1859-1950
Series II: James Stuart Douglas Papers, 1862-1974
Series III: Family Estates, 1934-1957
Series IV: Lewis W. Douglas Papers, 1906-1974
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, congressional bills, speeches, articles, financial records, clippings, diaries, reminiscenses, photographs of family members from 1897 to 1964, wills, and estate records relating to Lewis's family and his extensive activities in politics and government. Also includes material from his work with the Winston Churchill Foundation, 1958-1974; Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1940-1959; University of Arizona Institute of Atmospheric Physics, 1951-1972; and Southern Arizona Bank, 1949-1974. Also present is material on his investments in oil and mining companies,particularly the Copper Creek Consolidated Mining Company. Related to Arizona are his congressional work on copper tariffs, Colorado River water rights, and Indian issues; as well as committee work with many Arizona organizations concerning issues such as the Salt River Project, University of Arizona Medical School study, air pollution and smelter smoke, and a proposed Arizona nuclear site. Additional materials of his father and grandfather consist of family correspondence and records, and papers relating to mining technology and mining companies, especially Phelps Dodge Corp., 1863-1915. Correspondents of all three Douglases include many well-known figures in politics, mining, and world affairs.
Douglas, Lewis W. (Lewis Williams), 1894- -- Archives; Douglas, James S. (James Stuart), 1868-1949 -- Archives; Douglas, James, 1837-1918 -- Archives; Clemenceau, Georges, 1841-1929 -- Correspondence; Douglas family -- Correspondence; United States -- Congress -- (70th: 1927-1929); United States -- Congress -- (71st: 1929-1931); United States -- Congress -- (72nd: 1931-1933); United States -- War Shipping Administration; Copper Creek Consolidated Mining Company -- Records and correspondence; Phelps Dodge Corporation -- History -- Sources; Winston Churchill Foundation -- Records and correspondence; Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York -- Records and correspondence; New Deal, 1933-1939 -- Sources; Diplomatic and consular service, American -- Great Britain; Banks and banking -- Arizona; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Mines and mineral resources -- Mexico -- History -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Arizona -- Law and legislation -- Sources; Rain-making -- Arizona; Arizona -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- History -- Sources; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- Sources; United States -- Economic policy -- 1933-1945; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico) -- Water rights; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- United States; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: James Douglas Papers, 1859-1950
  - Subseries I: Personal Material
    - Awards and Honors. no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bills (Personal): clothing, food and wine, hospital supplies and equipment, jewelry and watches, paintings and art objects, photographic equipment, and miscellaneous. 1879, 1895-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical sketches and clippings. no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Book buying (Book dealers and publishers): Baker & Taylor (N.Y.), George Barrie & Son (N.Y.), Burrows Brothers Co. (Cleveland, OH), Cambridge Society (N.Y.), A.S. Clark (N.Y.), Congdon & Britnell (Toronto), Arthur G. Doughty (Quebec), E. Dufosse (Paris), P. Gagnon (Quebec), Thomas E. Hanel (Quebec), Henry Miller (N.Y.), and Bernard Quaritch (London). 1896-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Book buying, Egypt Exploration Fund. 1899-1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Book buying, Subscriptions; Miscellaneous correspondence. 1895-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Educational Certificates. no date (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Financial Notes and Records, income taxes. 1862-1867, 1894-1904, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Life insurance. 1896-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Personal Miscellany: two school compositions, business and personal calling cards, medical prescriptions, greeting cards, British Museum Reading Room Pass, invitations, "My Name in Morse Dots." no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Photographs and correspondence regarding. 1897-1904 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Travel arrangements and personal railroad problems. 1885-1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Will and Estate. no date (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Arizona Mining Journal and Engineering and Mining Journal, obituary notices. July 1918 and July 16, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Autobiographical recollections, I ("The Span of a Life"). no date (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Autobiographical recollections, II-VI. no date (Box 2, Folder 2-6)
    - Douglas Memorial Fountain at Nacozari. no date (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes (various subjects). no date (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (railroads). no date (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (various). no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous material (earthquakes). no date (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - In Memoriam: James Douglas (album of clippings regarding the death and estate of James Douglas). no date (Box 3)
  - Subseries II: Diaries, 1892-1916
    - Diary. 1892-1904 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Diary. 1905-1916 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III: Family Correspondence
    - Letterbook (J.D. to wife, sister, and others). 1871 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Naomi (Douglas) Douglas (wife). 1859-1911 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Naomi (Douglas) Douglas (wife), diaries. 1884-1889 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Walter Douglas (son). 1892-1915 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
    - Walter Douglas (son) and others. 1897-1905, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - James Stuart Douglas (son). 1881-1899 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - James Stuart Douglas (son). 1900-1917 (Box 6, Folder 1-9)
    - George Douglas (grandfather). 1764 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dr. James Douglas (father), includes correspondence about his father. 1855-1874, 1900-1918 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Elizabeth Douglas (daughter), includes her diary. 1887-1904, 1875-1876 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Commander Walter Douglas (father-in-law) and wife. 1849-1913 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Daughters and in-laws. no date (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Robert Cairns (uncle of Naomi, wife of James Douglas) and family. 1831-1899 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Lewis Williams (fahter of Josephine, daughter-in-law of James Douglas) and wife Hattie (Powell) Williams. 1861-1907 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Sir Archibald Douglas (cousin). 1905-1910 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - George M. Douglas (cousin). 1887, 1900-1915 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - David Dale (cousin). 1886-1916 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - John Callis (nephew) and family. 1900-1916 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Cousins and nephews. no date (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Mercer Family. 1885-1907 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Ross-Mercer Family. 1887-1889 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - James Bolton Douglas (brother-in-law). 1899-1905 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Miscellaneous family. no date (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IV: Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Arizona topics and problems. 1889-1916 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Education. 1899-1908 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Job requests. 1887-1905 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Lectures. 1898-1917 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Medicine. 1898-1911 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - American Museum of Natural History. 1896-1915 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Barlowe-Massicks, T.W. 1895-1915 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Brodier, Alexander O. (Governor of Arizona). 1899-1903 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Cook, W. and A.H. 1895-1915 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Cooke, Edward H. 1896-1904 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Darlington, Thomas. 1889-1902 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Iles, George. 1889-1918 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - LeMoine, J.M. 1897-1917 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - LeSueur, W.D. 1903-1904 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - McNair, F.W. 1902-1904 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Mauser, F.C. 1902-1915 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Murphy, N.O. (Governor of Arizona). 1901 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - New York Public Library. 1896-1909 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore. 1898-1899 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Stevenson, J.J. 1896-1900 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Stoddard, Isaac T. 1898-1903 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Various: Bymner, Douglas; Dawson, S.B.; Lummis, Charles F.; Smillis, W.C.; and Oates, Philip. 1888-1905 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous. 1876-1915 (Box 9, Folder 23-25)
    - Letters of introduction and recommendation. 1895-1905 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Subseries V: Mining Technology
    - Correspondence (T. Sterry Hunt). 1880-1888 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (Miscellaneous and various). 1875-1905 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Plans and drawings. no date (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous materials. no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Patents (Mexico). 1892-1898 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Patents (United States). 1863-1900 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Patents (Canada and Newfoundland). 1865-1881, 1893 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Consolidated Kansas City Smelting and Refining Co. 1888-1897 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Boston and Montana Consolidated. 1895-1901 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Fraser and Chalmers. 1888-1901 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Keyser. 1895-1902 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Krupp. 1894-1898 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Ledoux and Co. 1887-1915 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Langton, John. 1895-1901 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Moir, Robert. 1894-1905 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Musson, W.A. 1895-1897 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Peters, E.D., Jr. 1885-1889 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Walworth, J.A. 1878-1880 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - General correspondence. 1887-1915 (Box 11, Folder 13-16)
  - Subseries VI: Mines and Mining Correspondence
    - Bell, Robert. 1900-1910 (Box 12a, Folder 1)
    - Bouglise, G. de la. 1895-1903 (Box 12a, Folder 2)
    - Brooke, C.B. 1895-1902 (Box 12a, Folder 3)
    - Church, William. 1883-1898 (Box 12a, Folder 4)
    - Colqutioun, James. 1888-1905 (Box 12a, Folder 5)
    - DeKalb, Courtenay. 1899-1918 (Box 12a, Folder 6)
    - Dodge, Cleveland H. 1897-1917 (Box 12a, Folder 7)
    - Dodge, William E. 1882-1903 (Box 12a, Folder 8-11)
    - Greene, William C. and the Cananea Consolidated Copper Co. 1901-1904 (Box 12a, Folder 12)
    - Guggenheim (various). 1896-19005 (Box 12a, Folder 13)
    - Howe, Henry M. 1887-1915 (Box 12a, Folder 14)
    - James, D. Willis. 1888-1905 (Box 12b, Folder 1)
    - James, J. Stanley. 1902-1903 (Box 12b, Folder 2)
    - Kelly, Robert. 1877-1899 (Box 12b, Folder 3)
    - Kingdon, George. 1898-1913 (Box 12b, Folder 4)
    - Lewis, A. Hornby. 1887-1913 (Box 12b, Folder 5)
    - Lewisohn Brothers. 1888-1905 (Box 12b, Folder 6)
    - Logan, John P. 1881-1897 (Box 12b, Folder 7)
    - Lotichius, Heinrrich. 1895-1900 (Box 12b, Folder 8)
    - Martinez del Rio, Pablo. 1897-1905 (Box 12b, Folder 9)
    - Masters, Harris K. 1901-1905 (Box 12b, Folder 10)
    - Mills, C.E. (Supt., Detroit Copper Mining Co.). 1896-1908 (Box 12b, Folder 11-12)
    - Moore, Clarence B. 1894-1902 (Box 12b, Folder 13)
    - Notman, George. 1893-1908 (Box 12b, Folder 14-15)
    - Ore Concentration syndicate, Ltd. 1903-1904 (Box 12b, Folder 16)
    - Phelps dodge and Co. (General and Miscellaneous). 1883-1887, 1894-1914 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Phelps Dodge and Co. no date (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Probert, Frank H. 1900-1904 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Royal Ontario Nickel Commission. 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Southern Pacific Co. 1887-1905 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Trippel, Alexander. 1895-1896 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - U.S. Geological Survey. 1896-1904 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Van Vleck, Joseph. 1887-1901 (Box 13, Folder 9-12)
    - Vogelsang, Karl. 1895-1905 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Williams, Ben. 1887-1905 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - williams, Lewis. 1883-1896 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Woodhule, Maxwell. 1903-1905 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Bessemer Memorial Fund. 1903-1904 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Herring, William, and Mitchell, Thomas. 1892-1902 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Ricketts, L.D. 1887-1907 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Robertson, Wm. F. (Canada Department of Mines). 1899-1903 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Temple, C.V.M. 1902-1904 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Detroit Copper Mining Co. (Reports, etc). 1881-1882 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Pictou Iron Properties (Nova Scotia). 1875-1880 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Pie Island Silver Ore (Lake Superior). 1875-1880 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Prize Gold Mine (Colorado). 1884-1886 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - San Carolos Mines and O'Brien Claims. 1892-1905 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Storm Cloud Mines (Arizona). 1897-1905 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Lithographic Stone (Miscellaneous and general). 1893-1905 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Lithographic stone (Davis, J.W.). 1895-1904 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Lithographic stone (Sykes, C.P.). 1894-1900 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Lithographic stone (Wastell, E.T.). 1901-1905 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous reports, statistics, etc on mining. no date (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - J.D.'s letterbook; various notebooks and miscellaneous notes on mining. September 14-December 11, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence. 1856-1919 (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
    - Introductions, references, recommendations. 1887-1909 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Railroad correspondence (various). 1887-1911 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Subseries VII: Publications, speaches and lectures
    - Correspondence regarding Canadian Independence and New England and New France. 1894, 1913 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, clippings, etc. regarding Old France in the New World. 1905 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Letters to the Editor (various). no date (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Mining and metallurgy. no date (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Railroads. no date (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "Record of Borings in the Sulphur Spring Valley, Arizona," published in the Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, volume XL number 167. no date (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous articles. 1881-1905 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Book reviews. no date (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with Editors and Publishers ( Engineering and Mining Journal). 1888-1913 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Editors and Publishers ( The Nation). 1895-1906 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with Editors and Publishers (various). 1895-1905 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Speeches and lectures. no date (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Subseries VIII: Scrapbooks, 1881-1918
    - Contributions to the Engineering and Mining Journal. no date (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Contributions to The Nation. no date (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous contributions. no date (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IX: Memberships
    - Adirondack League Club. 1896-1915 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - American Institute of Mining Engineers. 1897-19005 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - American Institute of Mining Engineers (California meeting). September-October 1899 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Canadian Mining Institute. 1898-1911 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Canadian Society of New York. 1897-1905 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Institution of Mining and Metallurgy. 1896-1905 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - John Fritz Medal fund. 1903-1915 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Literary and historical society of Quebec. 1895-1905 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Railway Conductors' Club. 1896-1897 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Professional Organizations (various). 1898-1905 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1901
      American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1900
      American Philosophical Society, 1898-1905
      Archaeological Institute of America, 1911
      Columbia University, Institute of Arts and Sciences, 1913
      Engineering Magazine, library committee, 1904
      Engineers' Club, 1899-1904
      Franklin Institute, 1899
      Imperial Institute of the United Kingdom, etc, 1899-1900
      International Miners' Association, 1903
      Iron and Steel Institute, 1898-1905
      Lake Superior Mining Institute, 1904
      National Geographic Society, 1899
      New York Zoological Society, 1901
      North of England Institute of Minig and Mechanical Engineers, 1899-1905
      Societe de l'Industrie Minerale, 1901
      Southwest-International Miners' Association, 1902
    - Social Clubs and Community Groups (various). 1895-1917 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      Art Collectors Club, 1904
      Association for the Protection of the Adirondacks, 1902-1905
      Athenaeum, 1909
      Bisbee Gymnasium Club, 1903
      Blue Pencil Club, 1901
      Booklovers Library, 1900
      British Schools and Universities Club of New York, 1902-1904
      Century Association; Century Club, 1901-1904
      Country Club (Westchester, N.Y.), 1899-1904
      Horticultural Society of New York, 1900
      Manhattan Municipal League, 1903
      Mayor Gaynor Memorial Association, 1913
      Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society, 1899-1905
      Montomerency Fish and Game Club (Quebec), 1905
      National Historical and Biographical Society, 1899-1905
      Navy League of the United States, 1917
      Reform Club (N.Y.), 1897
      Saint Andrew's Society of the State of New York, 1902-1904
      Senkenberg Natural History Society (Frankfort), 1894
      Society of Arts (London), 1895-1904
      Toltec Club (El Paso), 1902
  - Subseries X: Philanthropy
    - Churches. 1895-1915 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Education. 1898-1914 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Libraries. 1894-1904 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Medicine. 1900-1918 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art. 1894-1911 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Salvation Army. 1897-1918 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Smithsonian Institution. 1895-1905 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous. 1895-1918 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Gifts of Books and Minerals. 1894-1917 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Various personal gifts, including money. 1895-1917 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous requests for money. 1888-1917 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - McGill University. 1896-1915 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Queen's University (Correspondence, speeches, etc.). 1900-1915 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Queen's University (council and trustees). 1900-1910 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Queen's University (N.Y. Society of Queen's University). 1901-1905 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Subseries XI: Property
    - New York, Douglas, Archibald (Attorney); Chrystie, Brightman & Douglas; and Douglas & Armitage. 1902-1916 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - New York, Cuthbert, Thomas N. (Attorney). 1899-1905 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - New York, McKelvey and Mattocks (Attorneys). 1898-1905 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - New York, Hudson Park (Putnam Property). no date (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - New York, Hudson Park (House of Archibald Douglas). 1903-1905 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - New York, Hudson Park Depot. 1892-1904 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - New York, Kingsbridge, N.Y. (Church and Library Property). 1902-1917 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - New York City, 53 E. 107th St. no date (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - New York, Riverdale (Delafield Estate). 1902-1918 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - New York, Spuyten Duyvil (House-building). 1896-1907 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - New York, Spuyten Duyvil (Grant of Land under water). 1899-1904 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - New York, Spuyten duyvel (Miscellaneous correspondence regarding property). 1892-1916 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - New York, Spuyten Duyvel Property (various). 1936-1937, 1946 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - New York, Spuyten Duyvil and Hudson Park Taxes. 1894-1897 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - New York, Park District Protective League. 1901-1905 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - New York, Apartment house development of Spuyten Duyvil Property. 1939 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Fort Lee Property, New Jersey. 1895-1907 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Old Forge Property, Little Moose Lake, N.Y. 1899-1904 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Amagansett, Suffolk County, N.Y. 1911 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Clinton, Conn. 1893-1908 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Miami, FL. 1899 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Farnborough, South Hampton County, England. 1903-1904 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Quebec, Canada (various). 1855-1864 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Offers to sell property. 1897-1916 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Subseries XII: Business
    - Herndon & Norris (Attorneys). 1896-1904 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Mortgage, Burke & Hickey (Prescott Hotel). 1895-1907 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Mortgage, Colby, Annie B. (cousin). 1904-1906 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Mortgages, various. no date (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Loan, Bassett, E.D. 1893-1903 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Loan, Buckler, Maggie. 1907-1908 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Loan, Ferrier, W.F. 1903-19005 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Loan, Holbrook, W.R. 1889-1905 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Loans, various. 1890-1916 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Investment, Douglas Improvement Company. 1902-1904 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Investment, Gatling gold & Silver Mining Company and Canada consolidated Gold Mining Company. 1880 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Investment, International Water Company. 1906-1908 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Investment, Molsons Bank (Montreal). 1899-1903 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Investment, Morenci Water Company. 1900-1905 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Investment, Port Arthur Iron company. 1899-1910 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Investment, Prescott National Bank. 1895-1905 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Investment, United Correspondence Schools. 1899-1902 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Investment, Woman's Hotel Company. 1899-1904 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Investments, various A-I. 1897-1905 (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Investments, various J-Z. 1886-1915 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - Subseries XIII: Lewis W. Douglas's Biography of James Douglas
    - Correspondence (H.H. Langton). 1938-1950 (Box 23, Folder 1a)
    - Correspondence (regarding missing J.D. papers). 1951-1968 (Box 23, Folder 1b)
    - Correspondence (various). 1921-1950 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Index to documents. no date (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Outline and notes. no date (Box 23, Folder 4a)
    - Introduction. no date (Box 23, Folder 4b)
    - Chapters 1-5. no date (Box 23, Folder 5-10)
    - Part II, Chapter I. no date (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - "Confession of Faith." no date (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Charles A. Nichols: "Four Generations." 1948 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - XIV: Microfilm of Material in Possession of Phelps, Dodge & Company
    - Microfilm of material in the possession of Phelps Dodge & Company. no date (Box 24a)
    - Microfilm of material in the possession of Phelps Dodge & Company: reels 1-12, 14-19. no date (Box 24b)
  - XV: Hood and Gown of James Douglas, McGill University
    - Hood and Gown. no date (Box 25)
  - XVI: Oversize Material